Picking a fight with Iran at this time
means that the United States, which they
know,
is basically having a war with Russia
and China.
And that's not a good idea
because those societies are equipped to
fight a lot longer than the United
States given everything we've seen in
previous wars that these countries have
gotten involved in.
Bad choice, bad timing.
>> I am John Kiriakou and welcome back to
Deep Focus.
Well, there's so much in the news,
whether it's Iran, Gaza, Ukraine,
whatever it is, oil,
it all comes back to economics. It
really does. There was breaking news
this morning. We're filming this on
April the 16th. Breaking news this
morning that Europe, listen to this, how
crazy this is. Europe will run out of
jet fuel in 6 weeks.
That would lead to an economic calamity
that will ripple across the entire
planet.
How in the world do we negotiate
something like this? How do we get out
of something like this? Well, I know one
man who has some answers. That's Dr.
Richard Wolff. Professor Wolff is host
of the Economic Update. He's director of
Democracy at Work. He's professor
emeritus of economics at the University
of Massachusetts at Amherst and he's
also a visiting professor at the New
School in New York. Professor, welcome
back. It's always such a pleasure to to
have you and I always enjoy it so much
not just because
you're from Youngstown, Ohio,
but because you speak in plain English
and Americans can understand you. Good
to have you back.
>> Thank you very much, John. You're
generous and I appreciate your kind
words.
>> Uh thank you very much for joining us.
I want to start with this craziness from
the Associated Press
that Europe will be out of jet fuel in 6
weeks.
Is there a precedent for something like
that? And whether there is or not,
uh how do we fix this?
>> Well, I don't know if there's a
precedent for it or not. Certainly not
very many. This is a
in many ways a newer version at least
of something that we've never seen
before.
Um
let me explain why it's happening
in the way that I think people need to
understand.
For most of the last 75 years,
the United States has been
either an enemy of Iran or a critic or
for a short time, the years when the
Shah of Iran ran that country,
a subordinate ally who who so upset the
Iranian people that when they finally
overthrew the Shah and drove him out of
the country,
he retired to the United States cuz that
was who he had protected him. That's
what who got him into power by
overthrowing the famous Mosaddegh
revolution back in 1953.
And then in in '79 and so on with people
who will remember uh
when the the Ayatollahs took over
the running the country, uh the United
States tried in every which a way
to make it difficult for them, to
overthrow them,
to challenge them, to fund and support
people inside Iran against the
government. That is nothing new.
And most of the time the United States
was more or less successful. In that is
it kept that country off its toes. It
made it difficult for Iranians to do
many things. It caused a large number of
Iranian professionals to leave the
country and take up residence. There are
huge communities of Iranians in the
United States. For example, in the Los
Angeles area, but likewise in Paris and
likewise in London.
It was a country that was besieged and
it culminated last June now about a
little less than a year ago when the
United States and Israel attacked uh
with bombs and missiles and all the rest
of it um in what came to be known as the
12-day war.
All right. So,
here's the point. Iran has had a very
long time and a very bitter experience
trying to figure out how to cope with
the enmity of the United States to which
I should add the even more ferocious
enmity of Israel. Israel has
designated Iran as its most horrible
adversary in the Middle East, etc., etc.
And so, they've been at each other for a
long time.
Okay.
What has now happened and what Americans
have to try to understand, whatever
their
likes or dislikes might be,
is that the Iranians
finally figured out a strategy
to confront the United States and
Israel.
They knew they could not compete on the
level of military confrontation. The
United States spends more on military
than the next eight or nine countries
combined. Um
Iran with its 90 million people is no
match for the United States with three
Excuse me, 330 million people and a
budget 100 times larger. So,
they had to come up with a different
strategy. They did.
And so far, it is working better than
anyone, including the Iranians, had
foreseen.
And I'm now going to show you how it
explains
the absence of jet fuel for Europeans.
What the Iranians decided they would do
if ever again they were attacked by the
United States or Israel,
overtly, covertly, or anything else,
is they would use what is by far their
greatest weapon.
And that is to close the Strait of
Hormuz. In other words,
they are in a position, I won't bore you
with the maps. I think many people have
now seen them. Uh this passageway, very
narrow, between the uh Arabian Sea and
the Persian Gulf,
through which about 20% of the world's
oil is transported,
and a good percentage of derivatives of
oil, things like jet fuel,
um things like plastic, and things like
fertilizers.
>> Fertilizer. 65% of the world's
fertilizer.
>> Yeah, made out of petroleum, shipped out
of that area uh where the petroleum is
is brought up.
They said they would do that. And when
the United States and Israel attacked
them roughly 45 days ago,
that's what they did.
They said, "We are not allowing Israeli
ships to go through here
people who ships registered to Israeli
owners
ditto for the United States
and ditto for any other country that
allies with Israel and the United States
in this war against us.
We are also going to show you that one
of the things we've developed is a
technology of drones and of missiles
and a specially effective way of hiding
the launchers for them
so that you cannot
you can get some of them, but you cannot
prevent us
from sending these things to your
country and doing damage.
Okay, the United States and Israel knew
all of that.
They attacked anyway.
That has to do with the American
government and the mechanisms in Trump
and the other folks that make those
decisions.
And then the Iranians did what they said
they would do.
They closed the Strait of Hormuz except
to a trickle of ships mostly carrying
Iranian oil to their conventional
customers. And I should make a footnote
people should learn.
The customers are Asia mostly. So Japan,
South Korea, Philippines, and China are
the buyers of
Iranian oil.
Not that they can't get oil elsewhere.
They can and they're doing that now. But
20% is a large amount of oil and a
disproportionate amount of that went to
those Asian countries.
But one of the things you can't do
is take oil from Iran to Europe.
That requires you
to move ships and so forth. You can't do
it.
So, here's an irony you should think
about.
Iran
closed the strait thereby controlling
the movement of oil
thereby depriving all kinds of receivers
of oil from the Middle East from getting
it.
Not just oil from Iran, but oil from
other parts of the Gulf states, UAE,
Qatar, Kuwait, Oman that have to go
through
uh
to get to where they can be used.
And what the consequence of this was
that
the oil that needs to be refined to
produce jet fuel
wasn't arriving at the factories that
convert regular petroleum to jet fuel.
The Europeans
uh here's crucial. The Europeans had not
been told by the United States about the
attack.
They had not been warned. They had not
had time to prepare.
So, they didn't.
Now, partly that's cheapness on the part
of the European airlines. They don't
want to spend very expensive. They don't
want to spend money on jet fuel and
store it for long periods of time. Uh
they assumed the United States
would coordinate with them in this war.
They were wrong. Mr. Trump didn't.
That is one of the reasons why two
things. One,
that when Mr. Trump
asked them for help halfway through the
war,
they basically said no. The British let
them use the base in Cyprus, but mostly
did not
uh support. And Mr. Trump attacked the
Europeans as he has done before,
furious that they weren't helping him,
utterly oblivious to the reason why,
which they told him.
Okay, so
footnote,
the anger, the bitterness of the
Europeans against the United States
cannot be over straight over stressed.
>> Yes.
>> NATO is dead, the alliance is dead, and
the blame for it is 100% on the US.
That's the view in Europe.
And most others who look at this see,
Mr. Trump did not sit down with the work
out all that crap about tariffs a year
ago.
And he didn't do it again this time.
And then it becomes doubly important
because Iran developed missiles that it
can send a very wide range, hundreds of
kilometers.
That's why it was able to destroy or
damage the 13 American military bases
that are in the Gulf region. That's why
it was able to penetrate very severely
the Iron Dome and David's Sling, the two
protective mechanisms the Israelis have
developed. So, they would turned out to
be vulnerable.
Those missiles could go to Europe. They
could hit European cities.
So, not to involve the Europeans
in a war where they were directly
vulnerable is driving them crazy with
anger and bitterness at being treated in
this way.
And America are going to have to deal
with that for years to come. That is a
very serious business because the
leaders of of Britain, France, and
Germany, the three major countries,
those leaders are all getting
between 10 and 20% poll ratings in their
polling. They are very unpopular. They
are not going to be in power much
longer. And what's driving them out is a
popular opinion that blames them for
being lackeys of Mr. Trump. And so this
is
We're going to come back You and I going
to come back and talk about this in the
future. Let me go back Let me go back to
the very briefly on the
on on on the Iranian thing.
The Iranian strategy
And I know this is going to scare
people, but
if you didn't want me to tell you the
truth, you wouldn't have asked me,
right? So,
um
The Iranian strategy is to say the only
way we can fight the United States, the
only way we can defend ourselves,
having been victimized over and over
again for 75 years,
is if we drive the United States
out
of the Middle East.
Close your 10 bases. Forget about it.
You you We're not going to let you stay
here.
We're going to bomb your bases if you
rebuild them.
It's going to become wildly more
dangerous, wildly more expensive for you
to maintain
this empire in this part of the world.
And to show you how serious we are,
you can bomb us till you're blue in the
face. Won't make any difference.
By the way, they have proven in 40 days
that that's not an empty threat. That's
what they did. You can bomb the school
with the 150
girl students that we saw or any or any
of the the bridges or whatever it is
you're going to do.
We will accuse you of being war
criminals.
Uh we're not going to cave in.
But here's more.
We're not going to let oil through
the the Strait of Hormuz.
And we understand that that's going to
drive the price of oil up. By the way,
that's already happened. The price of
oil is well in excess of $100 a barrel,
whereas before it was around 60 to 70
dollars a barrel. That That's a That's a
50% increase, and it is rising as we
speak right now.
Okay, that's going to produce likely in
the world a recession.
If it goes on long enough,
and by long enough I only mean a few
more months,
it will produce a global depression.
And if you're wondering, could it be as
bad as 1929?
I'm here to tell you, wearing my cap as
professional economist, it could. Will
it? I don't know. Could it? Absolutely.
And that means here's what the Iranians
are telling us.
We don't want to stop oil going through.
We didn't stop it.
Oil Something on the order of hundreds
of ships went through every day.
For years and years,
we were always there. We could have
stopped it. We have the missiles, we
have the drones, we have the boats,
we're right there. I mean, it would have
been childishly We didn't do it. So,
we're not closing the
strait.
American and Israel, they're the ones
who made the decision that led to the
show.
We're letting the world know
we are prepared
to let this play out.
To close the strait, drive up the price
of oil and also natural gas.
And the whole world
is going to have to face
either you help us
and you get the United States to change
its ways,
in which case the problem is solved. The
strait opens, the oil flows,
and we're back in business.
Or
you choose not to help us.
You don't care.
All right? Then you will live with
higher energy prices and all that that
may entail for your society, for the
recession, the depression, and all the
rest of it.
The Iranians don't wish the world harm.
The Iranians are not
inconsiderate of global opinion, but
they're explaining
they have no other option. And given the
attack and the ferocity of the attack
both from Israel and from the United
States,
it's hard to argue against their taking
this step uh whether or not you credit
their statements that it is nothing they
wanted to do.
>> Right.
I have another Iran question for you in
a moment, but first I want to read a
message from our sponsor.
Last week the Treasury Department put
out its financial report for 2025,
almost 2 weeks ago now. Almost no one
covered it. Certainly no one's talking
about it. But here's what it said.
The United States
has $6 trillion in assets, $47 trillion
in debt. The US government is $41
trillion
in the hole overall. That's not my
opinion.
Those are the Treasury Department
numbers. A few days ago, Fed Chairman
Jerome Powell said that the debt path,
quote, will not end.
His words. Meanwhile, the big beautiful
bill added $3 trillion more in debt, and
we're now paying more than a trillion
dollars a year in interest on the
national debt. I spent almost 15 years
in the CIA. I learned how to spot
problems before they blew up. Well,
right now, central banks all over the
world are buying gold as fast as they
can. China, Poland, India, they see
what's coming.
I've put together a free report along
with American Alternative Assets called
the Big Beautiful Bubble. It shows
what's really going on and how to
protect your savings before this gets
any worse. So, go to johnlovesgold.com
for your free copy. That is
johnlovesgold.com.
Or, if you prefer, call
1-888-G-O-L-D-0-5-3.
Professor,
I wanted to ask one other Iran question.
Um
the mainstream media
seems to be surprised that the Iranians
have been able to survive so well or so
far as well as they have. Well, I have a
very dear friend who travels to Iran
regularly. And, there's one recurring
theme every time she comes back from one
of these trips. And, that is with
crippling, punishing sanctions on Iran,
over the course of so many years, the
Iranians have become utterly
self-sufficient. If they need something
that they can't import from Russia or
China or India, they manufacture it
themselves.
Do you think they'll be able to keep
this up in the face of these hostilities
from the United States and Israel? Can
they Can they get through this conflict
economically?
>> I think now they can and and not to take
away from what you just said or to take
away in any way
from their resourcefulness.
Many Americans do not understand that
Iran is a well-industrialized
country. They have and have had for a
quite quite a while a serious commitment
to developing an industrial economy. So,
it's not like what Vietnam was or
Afghanistan was or Iraq was. It's These
are This is a different story, number
one.
So, my first answer is yes, I think they
can probably carry on for quite a while.
But, I want people to understand
cuz it Americans just they don't know
their geography.
Iran
and Russia
share an immense coastline of the
Caspian Sea. And they That's an internal
ocean in that part of the world. And
they can use that ocean to carry on
whatever trade they need. Do the
Iranians need something that gets
bombed?
The Russians put it on a boat and in in
a day and a half, it's done. It's in
Iran. Tehran is close to the Caspian
Sea. So,
very easy to to do this.
If the If the Iranians run out of
missiles and drones, by the way, no sign
of it, but if they were, that's another
Russia has shown us in Ukraine that it
has limitless amounts of those things.
And if Russia ever ran out, Russia and
China have thousands of miles of shared
border.
China, and I want to quote you Paul
Krugman from the other day, China's
manufacturing base
is larger than that of the United
States, Britain, France, and Germany
combined.
Right? So, the powerhouse manufacturing
in the world today is China,
not anybody else. China can produce
missiles and drones forever.
And it can ship them easily to Russia,
which can ship them easily to Iran.
Picking a fight with Iran at this time
means that the United States, which they
know,
is basically having a war with Russia
and China.
And that's not a good idea
because those societies are equipped to
fight a lot longer than the United
States, given everything we've seen in
previous wars that these countries have
gotten involved in.
Bad choice, bad timing.
>> I want to ask you also about the effect
of
Donald Trump's tariffs
compounded on this huge rise in oil
prices. Now, the Supreme Court ruled
that
most of these tariffs were
unconstitutional, that the Constitution
specifically says that only Congress has
the ability to levy tariffs. But, they
did throw the administration a bone by
allowing the Trump administration
temporary emergency tariff powers.
How damaging are these tariffs on the
overall economy?
>> Well, they're they're not very,
um, partly because
tariffs being a punitive
mechanism are a little bit like
sanctions, another punitive mechanism.
And the world has learned
over the decades,
in some cases over the century, tariffs
are very old. Countries have been
tariffing one another for centuries.
People have learned how to evade them,
avoid them, negate them, undermine them.
And all of that There's a whole
literature when I teach courses, there's
a whole segment where I give students
books and articles about how to go about
and they're just collections of
empirical studies of how these things
work. They do damage, they raise the
costs of all kinds of things, they are
unwanted.
Uh
but they are not anywhere near as
powerful
as the politicians who use them.
People should remember
much of what goes on in Washington is
carefully choreographed political
theater.
Mr. Trump wanted to show the world that
we're in charge.
And I can put a tariff on you like Thor,
you know, with a lightning bolt
hitting your tree and knocking it down.
Uh it was a demonstration
of power and importance.
And you might ask yourself cuz that
would be a good question. Why is the
president of the United States
in such a rush to do it
without getting the congressional
approval?
He could have got it.
His party controls both houses. He could
have got it. He didn't. Took an enormous
chance that somebody would contest it.
That was certain. And that the Supreme
Court would have to decide it. That was
likely. and he couldn't be sure.
Why would he do that? Because it's
theater. Because there's something that
the American people, he hopes, will
respond to.
Well, I think I know what that is.
And that is that the American empire,
and with it American capitalism, are now
declining.
In the 20th century, we were going up.
And that was a good ride for many of us.
But now we're going down. That's never
the same experience. We are going down.
And the decision of our
leaders is to pretend otherwise.
Uh it's what psychologists call denial.
So, during the last presidential race,
uh neither Trump nor Biden nor Harris
ever said a word about a declining
empire.
You know, we lost the war in Vietnam. We
lost the war in Afghanistan. We lost the
war in Iraq. We're losing the war in
Ukraine. You ought to begin to wonder
what that might mean.
Okay?
And empires are famous
for overreaching as they begin to
decline, only to discover that it
accelerates the decline.
>> I want to ask you too about
the uh the job market. February showed
significant job losses, and that was a
real reversal from previous months. So,
first, I wanted to ask you what your
forecast is for the next 6 months for
the labor market. And if if you don't
mind, I want you to also
factor in, or not even factor in, but
explain to us
um
the role of
the proliferation of strikes from from
Minneapolis to the to the Southern
California ports, and what impact
that might have on
rising union membership after years and
years of decline, on wages, and on an
economic recovery.
>> A quick answer to your question.
Capitalism, wherever it has settled,
has had an economic downturn, on
average,
every 4 to 7 years.
Europe, Asia, I mean, I don't know.
Well, that's the story. That's an
average, so sometimes you're above and
below it.
But, if you think about it, we've had a
a downturn, a crash,
uh by the way, we have many words,
recession, depression, crash, crisis,
downturn,
because it's always with us, every 4 to
7 years. So, we had the dot-com crash in
the spring of 2000. We had the subprime
mortgage crash
in 2008 and 9. We had the COVID-19
uh crash in 2020. Well, do the math.
It's 2026, we're due.
And so, if you read the financial press,
you'll see articles worrying about it.
If you add the shock
of the tariff regime, and now the shock
of the oil energy
explosion,
and the fact that we're due for one, my
prediction is, and by the way, here I
agree with Jamie Dimon, the head of
uh JP Morgan Chase, with whom I don't
agree on anything else, but I agree on
this, we're due for one. We're probably
going to have one, and it could very
well be very bad. If this war resumes
this weekend,
then all bets are off. Then then we
could be talking about a global
recession as bad as any we've had, and I
want to remind people the worst one was
still 1929 to 1940, a depression that
lasted 11 years,
whose high point of unemployment was
25%,
which is six times what it is today. Try
to imagine an America with six times the
unemployment. Anyway, fear of that,
beginning of adjustment to that, that's
provoking employers to squeeze the
workers who are beginning,
interestingly, to really fight back.
>> Professor Richard Wolff is host of
Economic Update. He's director of
Democracy at Work, Professor Emeritus of
Economics at the University of
Massachusetts at Amherst, and visiting
professor at New York
uh New York's New School. Professor,
thank you so much for uh joining us, and
thanks for giving us a little bit of
extra time.
>> My pleasure, John. And as I said, if you
want to continue, get in touch. I'd be
glad to continue the conversation with
you.
>> I'd love it. Thanks so much.